<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Summary reasons against the new oath &amp; Engagement. And an admonition to all such as have already subscribed it. With a cautionarie exhortation to all honest English spirits, to avoid the danger of perjurie by taking of it.</title>
            <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E585_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206265</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865437</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865437</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117677</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91292)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117677)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 90:E585[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Summary reasons against the new oath &amp; Engagement. And an admonition to all such as have already subscribed it. With a cautionarie exhortation to all honest English spirits, to avoid the danger of perjurie by taking of it.</title>
                  <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 [i.e. 14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeere 1649. [i.e. 1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Prynne.</note>
                  <note>Page 14 misnumbered as 16.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 22.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oaths --  Great Britain --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117677:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Summary Reaſons againſt the New
OATH &amp; ENGAGEMENT.</p>
            <p>AND
<hi>An Admonition to all ſuch as have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
Subſcribed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH
A Cautionarie Exhortation to all Honeſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh
Spirits, to avoid the danger of
Perjurie by taking of it.</p>
            <bibl>PROVERBS. 24. 21. 22.</bibl>
            <q>
               <p>My Sonne, feare thou the Lord, and the King: and meddle not with
them that are given to change.</p>
               <p>For their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of
them both.</p>
            </q>
            <p>PRINTED in the yeere 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117677:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117677:2"/>
            <head>Summary Reaſons againſt the New Oath and
Engagement.</head>
            <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ſhall Sweare, [or] I Declare and Promiſe, That I
will bee True and Faithfull to the Common-wealth of
England, as the ſame is now Eſtabliſhed WITHOUT
KING OR HOUSE OF LORDS.</p>
            <p>FIRST, This <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement</hi> is impoſed by thoſe
who, by the Lawes of God and the Realme, had never
any Power (admit them a full and free Houſe of
Commons, under no Force, as they are not) to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter,
much leſſe to Make or Impoſe any <hi>Oath</hi> in any Caſe.
<hi>Cookes 3. Inſtitut. p.</hi> 165. and leſſe Authority then the Biſhops
and Clergy in Convocation, who made the &amp;c Oath, not ſo bad
as this; adjudged high-Treaſon in <hi>Canterburies</hi> Caſe, for which
hee loſt his head: <hi>Canterburies Doome p.</hi> 26. 40. though not ſo
bad as this.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is contrary to all the antient Oathes of our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,
Juſtices of Peace, Mayors, Sheriffs, Recorders, Clearkes of
Chancery and other courts of Juſtice: To the Oathes of Fealty
and Homage, made by all the Kings Tenants: The antient and
late Oathes of Supremacy and Allegiance; the Vow and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation;
the ſolemne League and Covenant, and Engagement
of the whole Kingdome to the <hi>King, his Heires Succeſſours,
and Poſteritie for ever, to defend their undoubted Right to the
Crowne with the laſt drop of their Bloods,</hi> conteined in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes
of 1. <hi>Jacobi cap.</hi> 1. 2. and involves the Makers and Takers
thereof, in manifold execrable perjuries; to the ſcandall of our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117677:3"/>
Religion,<note place="margin">Levit. 19. 12.</note> Nation, <hi>[a] Diſhonour and high Diſpleaſure of God,</hi>
and <hi>juſt damnation</hi> of their Soules.<note place="margin">Deut. 5. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Jer. 5. 2. c 7 9.</note> It is a new <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon,</hi> blowing up the
King and his Poſteritie,<note place="margin">Ezech. 17. 12. <hi>to</hi> 20. Zech. 5. 3. 4. Mal. 3. 5.</note> Monarchy, the Houſe of Lords, the
Conſtitution and Priviledges of our Engliſh Parliaments, our
ancient fundamentall Government,<note place="margin">Math. 5. 34.</note> Lawes, Liberties, and our
three Kingdomes at one crack;<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 31 32. 2. Tim. 3. 3. 4.</note> the very ſame and farre worſe
then that of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> condemned by the Statutes
of 3. <hi>Jacobi cap.</hi> 1. 2. 4. executing farre more then what they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
and quite deleting the Infamy and memory of that, and
all future celebration <hi>of that joyfull day of November 5. never to
bee forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, It diſſeiſeth, diſinheriteth, fore-judgeth the King
of his<note n="b" place="margin">1. Jac c 1. 2 4. 3. Jacobi. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Rightfull Crowne and Revenues,</hi> the Houſe of Lords
of their Peerage, Priviledges, and<note n="c" place="margin">A Plea for the Lords.</note> the undoubted Rights our
Engliſh Parliament and Kingdom of their very Liberties and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;
un-Kinging, un-Lording, un-Parliamenting, un-King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doming
them all at once, without once ſummoning and <hi>bringing
them to Anſwer by any legall Proceſſe, to heare what they can ſay
for themſelves,</hi> and without any <hi>lawfull Judgement of their Peers
according to the Lawe of the Land,</hi> contrary to the expreſſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>E. 3. c. 9. 25. E, 3. c. 4. 28. E. 3. c.</hi> 3.
37, <hi>E. 3. c. 18. 42. E. 3. c.</hi> 3. and <hi>the Petition of Right;</hi> yea<note n="d" place="margin">Votes of <hi>Octob.</hi> 11. 22. 1649.</note>
               <hi>debarres theſe Miniſters, Officers, Lawyers, Students, from their
Augmentations, Callings, Offices, Preferments and Degrees, who
Refuſe or Neglect to Subſcribe it;</hi> contrary to all theſe Statutes
and the Lawe of the Land, without any hearing or Tryall;
the extremitie of Tyranny and Injuſtice; tranſcending
that of King, Prelates, Starre-Chamber or High-Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, It inevitably involves the Makers, Takers and Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
thereof in <hi>manifold</hi> High<hi>-Treaſons againſt King, Kingdome,
Parliament,</hi> for ſome of which only in a farre lower Degree,
<hi>Strafford, Canterbury</hi> and many <hi>others have loſt their Heads,</hi> as
you may read in Maſter <hi>St. John</hi>'s <hi>Argument</hi> againſt <hi>Strafford,</hi>
and Sir <hi>Edward Cookes 3. Inſtitutes cap.</hi> 1. 2. to the forfeiture
of their Lives, Eſtates, Soules; yea, Infamy and Ruine of their
Families.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117677:3"/>
Sixtly, It enjoynes us to bee <hi>True and Faithfull to the new
Common-wealth of England</hi> (the Generall Councell of Officers
of the Army; the new created Councell of State, and their <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi>
Conclave of Journey-men) <hi>as it is now Eſtabliſhed</hi>
WITHOUT KING OR LORDS (without conſent of
Kingdome, People or Parliament) by force of Armes, Treachery,
Perjury,  that is, to aſſiſt and <hi>defend them with our Lives,
Councells, Eſtates, and to ſubmit to all their</hi> (illegall) <hi>Acts and
Taxes</hi> (to the <hi>loſſe of Lives, Liberties, Properties againſt the
Kings or Lords juſt Titles;</hi> and our owne Lawes, Liberties,
Byrth-Rights; which to doe, is not only contrary to Lawe
(ſince no <hi>Homage</hi> or <hi>Fealty is due from any Subject, whatſoever,
to other Subject,</hi> but to the <hi>King alone, and with a ſaving of that
Faith which hee owes to our Soveraigne Lord the King,</hi> and that
only where <hi>there is a legall Tenure betweene them,</hi> as Sir <hi>Edward
Cooke</hi> Reſolves, 1. <hi>Inſtitutes f.</hi> 64. 65. 67. 68.) but no leſſe then
<hi>High-Treaſon</hi> within the Statute of 25. <hi>E. 3. c.</hi> 2. as he Reſolves
in his 3. <hi>Inſtitut. c.</hi> 1, and therefore unreaſonable and Treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
for ſuch as are True and Faithfull neither to King, Lords,
Parliament, Kingdome or People, to exact or expect from any
others.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, It moſt ingratefully and unworthily obliterates the
memoriall of all the good Lawes, Liberties, Franchiſes, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
Benefits, Deliverances wee have received, and the Peace,
Proſperity, Freedome and Happineſſe, Wee and our Anceſtors
have enjoyed under the Reignes of moſt Generous, Valorous,
Bountifull, Pious, Religious Kings and Queenes (eſpecially
our late renowned King, <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
King <hi>James,</hi> and a great part of King <hi>Charles</hi> his Reigne, which
the Parliaments in their Reigns in<note n="e" place="margin">15 <hi>H 8 c.</hi> 12. &amp; all Acts of the Subſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies granted by the Laity or Clergy in their reignes</note> ſundry <hi>Acts,</hi> our own &amp;
forreigne Hiſtorians and Writers have ſo highly <hi>magnified</hi> and
bleſſed God for; and our very laſt Parliament remembred and
thankfully acknowledged in ſome of their<note n="f" place="margin">Exact. Collection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 14. 15. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>96.</note> 
               <hi>Remonſtrances,</hi>
of which we need no other teſtimony but our<note n="g" place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection. <hi>p</hi> 712<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 713. 714.</note> 
               <hi>Kings</hi> &amp; <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation</hi>
Oath; in extirpating Kings and Monarchy for ever after,
for ſome confeſſed extravagancies and Errors of the beheaded
King, not halfe ſo grievous, oppreſſive, unjuſt or impious, as
thoſe themſelves are guilty of, eſpecially in Repealing as much as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117677:4"/>
in them lies the <hi>Oathes of Supremacy and Allegiance, and the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne
League and Covenant</hi> (the principall Bullwarks againſt the
Pope and Papiſts encroachments) and impoſing this new <hi>Oath
and Engagement,</hi> againſt the very Letter, Scope of theſe and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
other juſt and ancient <hi>Oathes,</hi> and forcing it againſt mens
Conſciences, to make them willfully perjured<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal 15. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rom 1 31 32</note> 
               <hi>and damne
their Soules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly; The maine end of this <hi>Oath</hi> is to extinguiſh, irradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
our Engliſh Monarchy and Kingſhip; though the<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal 22. 11 Pſal. 47 2. 7. Pſal. 29 10.</note>
               <hi>Government of God himſelfe over the whole World,</hi> and of our<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 1 6 Iſay 9. 7 Luke 1 33.</note>
               <hi>Saviour Jeſus Chriſt over his Church,</hi> who have the Titles of<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 10. 16 Pſal. 47 2. Pſal 89 18. Pſ 48 2 Pſ 95 3. Pſ. 149. 2. Pſ 33 17 20 1. Tim. 1 17.</note>
               <hi>King of Kings, &amp;c.</hi> ſo frequently given them in Scripture, though
the<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Seldius</hi> ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of honor part. 1. c. 1. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>firſt, antienteſt, univerſalleſt, honourableſt, freeeſt,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by Mr. <hi>Pym.</hi> himſelfe and the houſe of Commons <hi>Canterburie's</hi> doome <hi>p.</hi> 29 Exact Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions <hi>p.</hi> 696.</note> 
               <hi>beſt, happieſt, ſafeſt, peaceableſt, durableſt</hi> Government
of all others in the World; as the Scripture, Hiſtories, Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians
and Divines accord: That Government under which all
the Inhabitants of this Iſle, ſince it was firſt Peopled, have ever
lived, flouriſhed; continuing unalterable in all Changes and
Succeſſions of thoſe Nations which have invaded, peopled, or
Conquered it, as beſt and moſt agreeable and pleaſing to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple:
That of which we have ſo long experience, and enjoyed the
happieſt, freeſt, peaceableſt and moſt Religious we are ever like
to ſee; that which is eſtabliſhed, ratified with ſo many ſacred
<hi>Oathes, Lawes, Vowes, Acts, Records and Fences</hi> of all ſorts
that Piety or Policy could invent, that Impiety, Impudence and
Treachery it ſelfe might juſtly feare to invade it; and honoured
with ſuch ſignall preſervations and deliverances, in the Perſons
of <hi>Querne Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>King James,</hi> ſpecified in our Annals,
and<note n="o" place="margin">1 Jac. c. 1. 2 3. Jacobi c. 1. 2. 4.</note> ſome <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> as might daunt all <hi>Traytors</hi>
from attempting its ſubverſion; and all to introduce a Lowe-Country
Government, under as many Kings and Tyrants, as
there are <hi>new Lords, Officers, Souldiers,</hi> ſupported by a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
ſtanding Army, and conſtant Garriſons in all Counties;
which muſt bee maintained at the Kingdomes and Peoples charge
by a <hi>Perpetuall Exciſe ſo</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection. <hi>p.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>much declamed againſt in the
King,</hi> who did only once ſecretly <hi>attempt,</hi> (but not impoſe it)
great <hi>arbitrary Monthly Contributions,</hi> renued and augmented at
our new <hi>Governours</hi> meere pleaſures (who both impoſe, receive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117677:4"/>
and diſpoſe thereof as they pleaſe) and levy it by meere force
of Armes (reputed <hi>Treaſon</hi> in<note n="q" place="margin">Mr. <hi>St. Jonns</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at Law.</note> 
               <hi>Strafford's</hi> Caſe, and a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying
Warre againſt the <hi>King and Kingdome</hi>) and that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied
with the undoing peſt of<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Right 3. Caroli.</note> 
               <hi>Free Quarter,</hi> upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
March, or pretence of Arreares, or Pay: And what happy
free <hi>new State and Government</hi> this will prove (the very beſt
all rationall men muſt expect, being ſupportable only by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
Army, Garriſons, Exciſe, Contributions, &amp;c. as the Low-Countries
are) to juſtle out our ancienteſt Monarchy in the
World, under which wee were freed from all <hi>Armies, Garriſons,
Exciſe, Contributions, Free-Quarter,</hi> and feares of Forraigne
Invaſions, which now affright us, granting only a <hi>Subſidy or
two</hi> in devers yeares, only by <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> to which all
conſented (wherein the Commons never preſumed to Tax the
Lords and Clergy at their pleaſure, as they now unjuſtly doe,
without their own free conſents) amounting not to one Moneths
Exciſe and Contribution in many yeares; let all men judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before
they take or ſubſcribe this new <hi>Oath and Engagement</hi> to
aboliſh the one which was ſo eaſy, and erect the other, which
muſt of neceſſity prove ſo grievous.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, It will really verifiy and make good all the late
<hi>King's</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection <hi>p.</hi> 262. 282 284 to 289. 297. 298. 500. 514. 517. 521. 522. 526. 528. 530 531. 534 550 551. 554 558. 561. 562. A Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 177 worthy our ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</note> 
               <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrances</hi> againſt the proceedings
of the late <hi>Houſes</hi> of <hi>Parliament;</hi> wherein Hee prophetically
and frequently charged them (or rather <hi>a few Factious and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious
diſcontented spirits, that over-ſwayed and ſeduced them,
under the ſpecious pretences</hi> OF RELIGION <hi>and</hi> LIBER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY)
<hi>with a Trayterous</hi> RESOLUTION <hi>and</hi> DESIGNE
<hi>to alter, destroy, diſſolve, ſhake, and rent in pieces the whole frame
and conſtitution of this Kingdome, ſo admirably framed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
by the bleſſing of God and the wiſedome of our Ancestors to
the wonder and envy of all the Neigbouring Kingdomes. To turne
the well founded Monarchy into a Democarcy: To ruine Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy
it ſelfe and Regall Power, never before ſtrucken at, To De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
Murther, and Deſtory both Himſelfe and His Royall Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
and Diſſolve His Government and Authority. To alter and
ſubvert the ancient Frame, Conſtitution, and Government of Church,
State, Parliament, and Fundamentall Lawes, Liberties of the
Kingdome and People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To destroy the houſe of Lords<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117677:5"/>
Rights and Freedome of our Parliaments: To ſubject
both King and People, Lawes and Liberties, together with His and
his good Subjects Lives and Fortunes, and bring them into perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
ſlavery and bondage to their Vaſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlimited, Lawleſſe, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary,
Seditious, Juriſdiction, Tyranny, Power Government,
(which would revive that Tragedy Mr.</hi> Hooker <hi>relates of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abaptiſts
in</hi> Germany) <hi>and to deſtroy both Religion and Liberty,
King and People; over which they deſigned to make themſelves
perpetuall Dictators:</hi> And that <hi>their Armies were raiſed pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely
to effect all theſe Deſignes:</hi> (all which wee now finde effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
and fully accompliſhed by the treachery of the Army and
thoſe now acting) <hi>The timely prevention whereof, the King and
his Party profeſſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was the only end and Deſigne of taking up Armes
againſt them, for the preſervation of Religion, Lawes, Liberties,
Monarchy, and prevention of this fore-ſeene Anarchy, Tyranny,
and Confuſion, now brought upon us by our new pretended Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
(through perjury, treachery, and violence) againſt the Votes
and Remonſtrances of both houſes, who particularly</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection. <hi>p.</hi> 695. 696 657 658 A Collection, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 420. to 428 698 699. 700. 877, 878.</note> 
               <hi>Renounced
and Proteſted againſt them;</hi> And whereof the <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave
in the 16. and 17. pages of their <hi>late Declaration of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
laſt (ordered to bee read in Churches) doe ſufficiently acquit
both Houſes, and thoſe who adhered to them only out of honeſt
and publique Intention; <hi>as Deſignes of their owne,</hi> not <hi>revealed
till of late,</hi> the <hi>timely diſcovery whereof would have deterred all
from attempting or adhering to the chiefe Contrivers of them.</hi> Now
our ſubſcription to this <hi>new Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement,</hi> will <hi>poſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,</hi>
make both our ſelves, the late Houſes, and all their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
apparently guilty of all theſe <hi>trayterous horrid Deſignes</hi> (to
which they were no wales privie nor aſſenting, but ever abjured
in their <hi>Proteſtation, Vow, Solemne League and Covenant,</hi> and
abhominated from their ſoules) and thereby not only verifie
but juſtifie the <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the King in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
particular, as moſt Juſt, Neceſſary and Honourable for
the publique Liberty and Safety; but likewiſe canonize (as it
were) him with all his ſlaine and ſuffering Party, as <hi>Martyrs
for the Kingdomes and Peoples Safety,</hi> and the <hi>Publique Liberty;</hi>
(for which they loſt their lives and eſtates; as all <hi>Preſcribers</hi> and
<hi>Subſcribers</hi> of this <hi>Oath and Engagement</hi> muſt now neceſſarily
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117677:5"/>
acknowledge, and all the World will conclude againſt them)
and brand our ſelves, our Bretheren of <hi>Scotland</hi> and all thoſe
who have loſt their lives, limbs and eſtates in oppoſition or
warres againſt them, with both the late <hi>Houſes,</hi> for <hi>notorious
Rebells, Traytors, Conſpirators, Murtherers;</hi> on whoſe <hi>Heads</hi>
and <hi>Soules</hi> the guilt of all the <hi>precious blood</hi> ſhed in our late and
preſent Warres, both in <hi>England, Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> muſt
now bee tranſlated from the King and his Party (on whom wee
have formerly charged it) and juſtly reſt for the future, to their
eternall infamy, condemnation, ruine. Which unavoyda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
conſequence of our ſubmiſſion and ſubſcription to this <hi>Oath</hi>
and <hi>Engagement,</hi> with the horrers of Conſcience, and divine
Judgements that muſt neceſſarily ſeize upon us, when under
the guilt of ſo much <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Blood ſhed,</hi> is ſufficient of
it ſelfe alone to deterre us from the leaſt aſſent thereto, and to
engage our utmoſt power againſt them, without any other
arguments; 'ſpecially if compared with the Loyall and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall
reſolutions and engagements of our Anceſtors in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
at <hi>Lincolne. An. 28. E.</hi> 1. (Recorded in <hi>Walſingham
Hist. Angliae. p.</hi> 49. to 56. <hi>Cookes 2. Inſtit. p. 97. 98.) 20. H.
3. ch. 9. 40. E. 3. rot. Parl. n. 8. Cookes 4. Inſtit. p.</hi> 13. 14.
The notable Statute of 16. <hi>R. 3. c.</hi> 5. of <hi>Praemunire. 11. H. 7.
c. 18. 19. H. 7. c. 1. 25. H. 8. c. 22. 35. H. 8. c. 1. 1. Mariae.
Parl. 2. ch. 1. 1. Eliz. c. 1. 3. 5. Eliz c. 1. 23. Eliz. c.</hi> 1. 2.
1. <hi>Jacobi ch. 1. 2. 3. Jac. ch. 1. 2. 4. 5. &amp; 7. Jac. ch.</hi> 6. which
all <hi>perjured Judges, Sergeants and Lawyers</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho have diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured
their profeſſions by their late ſubſcriptions, and exceeded
<hi>Judge Thorpe, Treſilian</hi> and his companions, and the <hi>Ship-Money</hi>
Judges, in their <hi>Perjuries</hi> and <hi>Treaſons</hi> againſt <hi>King,
Kingdome, Lords, People, Lawes, Liberties,</hi> which they have
baſely and wickedly betrayed, againſt their Science and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience)
may doe well to chew the cudde upon and on Mr. <hi>St.
Johns Speech</hi> at the <hi>Impeachment of the Judges</hi> concerning <hi>Ship-Money,</hi>
and Argument at Law at <hi>Straffords Attainder</hi> (enough
to hang and damne them all twenty times over, with all other
Impoſers and Subſcribers of this <hi>Treaſonable Engagement</hi>)
doe well to-head other <hi>Straffords</hi> whoſe crimes were not halfe
ſo treaſonable and abhominable as the enforcing or ſubſcribing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117677:6"/>
of this <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement,</hi> by the meete pretended Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of thoſe, who never had the leaſt legall power to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
any old lawfull Oath, in any caſe, when a full free and
lawfull Commons Houſe; much leſſe to make and impoſe a
new treaſonable and illegall Oath of Allegiance to themſelves
(who are oblieged by no ſuch reciprocall Oath to preſerve our
Lawes, Liberties and free Cuſtomes, as our Kings alwaies
were) upon all the Nation, againſt the Lawes and Statutes of
the Realme, and above thirty legall Oathes yet in force, which
ſundry Officers are oblieged to take before they may or ought to
execute their reſpective Offices.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, The Scripture is expreſſe, that <hi>Monarchicall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
is Gods owne ſpeciall Ordinance, Deut.</hi> 17. 14 15. and <hi>Prov.</hi>
8. 15. 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 2. That the enjoyment of <hi>Kings and
Kingly Government is a great honour, happineſſe and benefit to
a Nation and a ſpeciall bleſſing promiſed and given to them by God
himſelfe, Gen. 17 6. 16. Jer. 17. 25 c. 22. 4 2. Chron. 9. 8.
Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch.</hi> 16. 13. And can it then bee a miſerie and Judgment to
us? that is a <hi>moſt ſevere Judgement</hi> of God, and the cauſe of
many miſeries, oppreſſions, diſorders and deſtruction to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
or Kingdome, to bee without a King, by the Scriptures
and Gods owne Reſolution. <hi>Judg. 17. 6. c. 18. 1. c. 19. 1. c. 21.
25. Hoſea 1. 4 c. 3. 4 5. c. 10 3. Jer</hi> 22. 3. to 13. <hi>Hoſea 13.
11. 12. Mich. 4. 9. 10. Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s 1. 13. 14 15. Zech.</hi> 9. 5. And
can it bee then any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>appineſt and no judgement unto us to bee
without a King? That Kings have beene the <hi>greateſt Reformers
and Promoters of Gods Worſhip and Religion and ſuppreſſors of
Idolatry under the Law</hi> (is the Bookes of <hi>Kings, Chronicles,
Ezra, Eſter, Nehemiah, Daniel</hi> the <hi>Pſalmes, Proverbs</hi> teſtify)
and are ſpecially <hi>prophecied and promiſed to bee the chiefe Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots,
Fathers, Promoters, Propagators and Reformers of Religion,
Gods Church and Worſhip under the Goſpell,</hi> in ſundry texts, as
<hi>Pſal. 62. 29. Pſ. 72. 10. 11. Pſ. 112. 15. Pſ. 138. 4. 5. Pſ.</hi> 148.
11. <hi>Iſay 41. 2. c. 45. 1. 2. 5. c. 49. 7. 23. c. 52. 15. c. 60. 3. 10. 11. c.</hi> 62
2. <hi>Rev. 11. 15. c.</hi> 21. 24. which Hiſtories witneſſe to bee expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally
verified, and more eſpecialy in our <hi>Iſland</hi> (according
to that Prophecio <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 10. relating unto <hi>Iſlands</hi>) which had
the fift <hi>Chriſtian King</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Math. Weſt. An 185. 307. Speed, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win, Spelman, Uſher, De Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Brit. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> 
               <hi>Lucius,</hi> and firſt moſt renouned
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117677:6"/>
               <hi>Chriſtian Emperor, Conſtantine the Great,</hi> borne and Crowned
in it; and many pious, devout and <hi>religious Princes</hi> ſince, of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
and later times, by whoſe <hi>bonnty, care, zeale; religion</hi> and
<hi>learning</hi> were advanced, continued and propagated amongſt us,
and are now likely to expire with our Monarchy, for want of
protection, maintenance, encouragement, and puniſhment of
Atheiſme, Hereſy, Blaſphemy and Prophaneneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and defrauding
Miniſters both of their Tythes and promiſed augmentations,
eating them out with taxes, &amp; turning them out of their Livings
and livelihood, by arbitrary Committees againſt Law and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
upon the bare ſuggeſtions of every malicious Sectary, or
Tythe-declaiming proſecutor. Upon which grounds Chriſtians
under the Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll are in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>firſt place enjoyned to make prayers,
interceſſions and thanks-givings for Kings that under them they
may live a peaceable life in all Godlineſſe and Honeſty:</hi> FOR
THIS IS GOOD AND ACCEPTABL IN THE SIGHT
OF GOD OUR SAVIOUR (therefore to aboliſh Kings is
ſinfull and diſpleaſing in his fight, and contrary to his reavealed
will) 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1. 2. To <hi>ſubmis to Kings as unto the Supreme,
and honour them for the Lords ſake; for ſo it is the will of God.</hi>
1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 13. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15. 17. To <hi>bee ſubject to Principalities and Powers.
Tit. 3. 1. Rom.</hi> 13. 1. which Scriptures muſt bee raiſed out of
the Bible as Apocriphall, if wee will extirpate Kings and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy
out of the Realme and Chriſtian World, as ſome now
endeavour: the attempting whereof muſt needes bee an high
affront to <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, which robs him of one of his moſt
glorious Goſpell Titles, <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords. 1 Tim.</hi>
6 15. <hi>Rev. 17. 14. c.</hi> 19 16. Ad to this, that the Scripture relates
it a great <hi>honour and proſperity to a Nation to become a Kingdom.
Ezech.</hi> 16. 13. and a great <hi>judgement, miſery, and diſhonour to bee
un-Kingdomed, or made a baſe, or no Kingdom. Jer. 16. 7 9. c.</hi> 22.
4 5 6. <hi>&amp;c. Ezech. 29. 14. 15. Dan. 11 9. Hoſea 1 4 Dan.</hi> 2. 44.
That the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and <hi>Heaven</hi> it ſelfe are
alwaies and<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 145. 11. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iſay 9 7 Dan. 4 35. c. 6. 27. Math. 3. 2. c. 5 7. 19 c. 12. 18 c 21. 43. c. 25. 34. c. 26. 25. u. 3. 33. c. 10 11 1. Cor. 6. 9. Col. 1. 13. 1. Tim. 4 1. 18 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. 5. 2. Pe. 1 11. Rav. 12. 10.</note> very <hi>frequently</hi> ſtiled a <hi>Kingdom</hi> never a Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
or Republique (in contradiction to a Kingdome) throughout
the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New-Teſtament.</hi> That the higheſt honour <hi>Christ</hi>
hath purchaſed for us with his moſt precious blood is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to <hi>make
us Kings to God his Father:</hi> to admit us into his <hi>Kingdome of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117677:7"/>
Grace here, and of Glory hereafter, where we ſhall reigne as Kings
for ever. Rev. 1. 5. 6. c. 5. 10 Lu. 1. 13. 1. Theſſ. 2. 12. 2. Tim.</hi> 4. 18.
And that the <hi>Kingdomes</hi> only (not States and Republ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>of
the Earth</hi> are Prophecied and Promiſed to become the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
of the Lord, and of his Christ. Pſ. 8. 31. 32 Rev. 1. 15. Obad.</hi>
21. upon all which conſiderations, we can never ſubſcribe to
the extirpation of our Kingly Government, or tranſlating our
ancienteſt Kingdome into the punieſt Republiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the World
for feare wee loſe Gods protect on of and intereſt, reigne, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
by his Ordinances in our Kingdome, and be for ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his Kingdomes of Grace, Glory, and from reigning
as Kings in either of them, which the preſcribers and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of this <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement</hi> (who uſurpe upon Gods ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
prerogative to diſpoſe of the <hi>Kingdomes of the Earth at his
own pleaſure. Da. 4 32. 17. Je.</hi> 18 6. 7. 9.) againſt ſo many Oaths,
Covenants, Reaſons, Scriptures, have cauſe to feare and expect.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, Wee are perſwaded in our conſciences, that the
change of our rightfull King into many new ſelfe created States,
our Kingdome into a Common-Wealth, and ancien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of King, Lords and Commons into a new Repreſentative
of Commons alone without King or Lords, the principall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne
of this new <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement,</hi> againſt ſo many Oaths,
Lawes, and Engagements of former &amp; later times inviolably to
preſerve them with our lives, eſtates, &amp; laſt drop of our bloods,
and that by the far leſſer part of the Kingdome and Houſe of
Commons, againſt the wills and Proteſtations of the Major part
who are moſt concerned therein, and without hearing their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
and objections to the contrary, or convincing them of the
neceſſitie or conveniency thereof by a free hearing and debate
thereof, in a full and free Parliament ſpecially convened for that
purpoſe; is not only a moſt unjuſt, illegall and tyrannicall act,
contrary to the Lawes of God, Nature and the Realme, a great
ſcandall to our Religion, and injury and diſhonour to our whol
Engliſh Nation, not to be preſidented in any age, eſpecially by
ſo great pretenders to publique Liberty; but likewiſe an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
of ſuch dangerous conſequence, as none endowed with
right Reaſon, the feare of God, or any reall love to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
durſt once for to attempt, as is clear to us by theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117677:7"/>
1. It will involve us in perpetuall Warres and troubles ſo
long as there are any of the blood Royall who have title to the
Crowne, or any of the Nobility endowed with any ſparkes of
honour left alive; who will never deſiſt from attempting the
recovery of their loſt Rights and Priviledges.</p>
            <p>2. It will ſever the united Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi>
from, and engage them and all the Kings forraigne friends and
Allyes againſt us; and neceſſitate us to mainta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a perpetuall
Army and Garriſons by Land, and Navy by Sea; which will
undoe us, with Contribution, Exciſe, Free-Quarter; expoſe us
to perpetuall Murthers, Robberie, Outrages, Tumults, Opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
Diſcontents; Decreaſe and Decay all Trading, and end in
our abſolute Slaverie, Miſerie, Ruine.</p>
            <p>3. It will neceſſiate our new Governours, after the ſale of
the Kings and Deanes and Chapters Lands, to help eaſe the
People (for a time only) and ſupport their Army and Navy, to
ſeize and ſell the Lands of all Corporations, Companies, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
Hoſpitalls, Schooles, and Rectories of Churches in the
Kingdome (a thing already projected by ſome) and to find out
ſome device or other to make new Delinquen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of purpoſe to
Sequeſter and Confiſcate their Eſtates, till the whole Kingdome
be Sequeſtred &amp; made Malignants to help pay the Soldiers: one
feared Deſigne of this new <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement</hi> againſt thoſe
who out of grounds of conſcience, Law and ſolid prudence,
refuſe to ſubſcribe it,</p>
            <p>4. It will diſſolve all our ancient Leagues with forraigne
Kingdomes and States, made only with our King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
and by the Law of Nations give them advantage and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
to ſeize our Ships, Merchants, Merchandize without
breach of League, in the behalfe of the King and thoſe who ſtand
for the Kingdomes continuance, with whom only the Leagues
were made and ſtand firme againſt others who oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>5. It will loſe our Intereſt, honour and reputation in and
withall other Kingdomes or States, who will refuſe to owne or
treat with us a State, thus forcibly and treaſonably erected; on
elſe treat with us, as the punieſt and meaneſt State in the
World, whoſe Agents and publique Miniſters muſt give place
to thoſe of all Kings, Princes and other States whatſoever
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117677:8"/>
which are ancientes then it, ever by the [u] <hi>Law of Nations
and reſolution of all Heranlds;</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Caſſanae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Catalogue gloriae Mundi Hiſt of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll of Trent.</note> which the generoſity of the
Engliſh Nation (the anci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntſt and firſt Chriſtian Kingdome in
the Chriſtian World<note n="x" place="margin">Seld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns <hi>Titles of Hen.</hi> part. 2. ch. 11.</note> claiming proceedency of all other
Kingdomes in Generall Councells add Aſſemblies heretofore)
will hardly brooke.</p>
            <p>6. It will null, diſſolve and extinguiſh all the Corporations,
Tenures, ancient Cuſtomes, Rents, Services, Courts of Juſtice,
ancient Seales, Proceſſe, Writs, Legall Proceedings, Charters,
Liberties, Cuſtomes, Forfeitures unpon penall Lawes, Titles
of Honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that are either hereditary or during life, and currant
Coynes of the Kingdome; which being derived only the Kings
and ancient Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> for them, their Heires and
Succeſſors, or reſerved to them, their Heires and Succeſſors, and
none others, and bearing their ſtamp and image on them; muſt
all fall, expire and vaniſh together with them, as the Houſe falls
all to pieces when the foundation is ſubverted; the Rivers quite
faile when the ſprings from whence they flow, the effects ceaſe
when the cauſe is deſtroyed, and the deriva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ives expire and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
quite away when the primitives are aboliſhed: And what
confuſions and miſchiefes will enſue, let the World judge.</p>
            <p>7. If wee ſhall once give way that our Kings, Kingdome,
Peers, and Parliaments; ſetled, eſtabliſhed, ſecured and fenced
with ſo long Preſcriptions, Lawes, Oathes, Covenants, Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
and Securities of all ſorts that humane wiſdome can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent,
ſhall be thus overturned, deſtroyed, diſſipated, annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in a moment, at the wills and luſts of our preſent Uſurpers,
againſt all their Solemne Oaths, Covenants and Proteſtations
not to doe it; wee cannot but imagine, conceive and believe,
that every particular perſons eſtate, goods, life, liberties and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments
in the Kingdome not halfe ſo well eſtalibſhed and fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
as they, can be ſecure or exempt from their violence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; rapine
but ſubject to their lawleſſe wills, courts, acts, ſeizures &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals,
to deprive us of them at their pleaſures; which will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
us the miſerableſt &amp; ſlaviſheſt People under Heaven, inſtead
of a free Republick; of which the late illegall proceedings in
martiall arbitrary Courts and Committees againſt the beheaded
King, Lords and others, with their late impoſed arbitrary Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117677:8"/>
Exciſes, Acts for new Treaſons, and this very <hi>Oath</hi> and
<hi>Engagement</hi> give us undeniable experiments.</p>
            <p>Upon which, and ſundry other weighty conſiderations, we
are pere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptorily reſolved, by the grace and aſſiſtance of our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnipotent
God, rather to endure ten thouſand S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>queſtrations,
Impriſonments, Deaths; then to betray our King, Kingdomes,
Parliaments, Lawes, Liberties, Religion, all our earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts,
wound our Conſciences, damnour immortall Souls by our
ſubmiſſion or ſubſcription to this irreligious, fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gitious, pernic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
ſcandalous, illegall, irrationall, unconſcionable, treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
New <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement;</hi> and adhere to the death con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
and ſincerely to our former <hi>Oathes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Covenants</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements,</hi>
which they diametrically oppoſe, maugre any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans
powers or forces whatſoever.</p>
            <p>To cloſe up all wee heartily wiſh all perjured Preſcribers of
this New <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement</hi> (eſpecially apoſtate Aſſembly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vines and Lawyers, who contrary to their former
<hi>Oathes, Covenants, Proteſtations</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptions</hi>) have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
this new <hi>Oath,</hi> Conſcienciouſly and ſadly to conſider
and peruſe: <hi>Levit. 19. 12. Pſal. 15. 1 2. 4. Ioſh. 9. 18. 19. 20.
2 Sam. 21. 1. &amp; 1 King. 1 29. 30. c. 2. 42. 43 46. 2 Chron. 13.
5. 6 &amp; Neh. 5 12. 13. Ier. 34. 8 to 20. Ezech. 17. 11. to 22.
Zech. 5. 1. to 5. Mal. 3 5 Rom.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 28. 31. 32. 2 <hi>Tim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. 1. to</hi> 6.
Dr. <hi>Beards</hi> Theatre or God Judgements <hi>L. 1. c.</hi> 27. 28. of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers
divine puniſhments (eſpecially the example of <hi>Rodulph.
p.</hi> 174. with another of that nature <hi>p.</hi> 176. and the example of
that perj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red Uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>per of the Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, againſt his <hi>Oath,</hi> King
<hi>Hera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld Math. Weſt. An. 1066. p.</hi> 430. 438. with the ſad Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
of Archbiſhop <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> tortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s of Conſcience, and Mr.
<hi>Bilneys</hi> for ſubſcribing againſt their Conſciences to ſave their
Lives, in Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> his Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments: And then they will eyther
with <hi>Peter,</hi> after he had abju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed his Lord and Maſter with an
oath, goe forth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bitterly, if they have any ſparkes of
Grace or hopes of Salvaſion remaining in them; or elſe with
tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cherous <hi>Iudas,</hi> who betrayed his Lord and Maſter to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
the High-Prieſts, goe out deſpairing, and hang themſelves
to avoid the ſhame of the World, and anguiſh of their torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Conſciences.</p>
            <div type="query">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:117677:9"/>
               <head>A Quaere touching an Engliſh Monarchy, and a Low-Country
Free-State; which of them is the
Freeſt, and moſt to bee deſired.</head>
               <div n="monarchy" type="answer">
                  <head>An Engliſh Monarchie,</head>
                  <p>Is a moſt Honorable free Government by an hereditary King ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Lawes of the Kingdoms, ſupplyed only (without any
ſtanding Army, Garriſons, Free-Quarter, Exciſe, or Monethly
Contributions, by a bare Ordinance of a few Commons) with a
Subſidy or two, in divers yeares, freely granted by the Laity and
Clergy in full Parliament by diſtinct Acts of Parliament.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="free state" type="answer">
                  <head>A Low-Country Free-State,</head>
                  <p>Is an Ignoble Servitude under the Militarie Command of many
ſelfe-Created new States, erected and ſupported by the meere Power
of a ſtanding Army, conſtant Garriſons, Citadels, accompanied
with perpetuall Monethly Contributions, Taxes, Exciſes and
Free-Quarter impoſed on the Clergy &amp; Laity by theſe new States
alone, without common conſent or Act of Parliament, and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
and diſpoſed of at their owne Will and Pleaſures.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Utrum horum mavis, accipe.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <pb facs="tcp:117677:9"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
